Let me stop you right there.
My name's Ollie.
It might surprise you,
but this isn't the worst day of my life.
Oh, no, no, no, no, no.
That happened a long time ago,
when I was a kid.
As long as I can remember,
curiosity has always
seemed to get the better of me.
Oh, hey, Dad. Um… Uh…
Thirsty?
Ollie, you never trust any other creature.
My little Ollie-kins!
I made you a new harvest hat.
He went off island.
You went off island?
Mom, you wouldn't believe what I saw.
It was incredible.
There was these leaves with eyes.
Oh, oh, and this giant fish
with rainbow scales smiled at me.
Really? Big rainbow fish?
I don't care! You don't go off island.
- But why?
- Because it's dangerous, that's why.
We're worried about you.
I don't see what the big deal is.
I was just exploring.
Son, the Pookoo
aren't supposed to be curious.
What's our motto?
- "Hide today, alive tomorrow."
- Exactly.
That's why we're blessed
with our Pookoo nose,
so that we can smell threats
and stay away.
We smell everything,
but not everything is a threat.
That's it. I'm telling him the Tale.
Caloo! No
Wait. The Tale?
As in the Tale the Tale?
I want to hear it.
He's too young to hear about the… wolf.
He'll have nightmares.
I won't. Lodd's parents told him.
I don't think we should be taking advice
from Lodd's parents.
Oh my goodness, come on.
- What the--
- He needs to know!
Grandma?
With the wind whistling eerily
through the hallows,
the dark one came
on a black and cloudless night.
The great destroyer who ignited hellfire
torched the Valley.
Oh wow. This is gonna be awesome.
You want to dial it back, please?
No!
It all started a long time ago
when the Valley
was a very different place.
The Pookoo didn't always
live on an island like we do now.
They lived amongst the other animals…
…in fear of the ferocious wolf
who stalked the Valley.
But then everything changed.
Into the Valley came a creature so huge,
the Dzo, the magnificent walking orchards.
In their vast wisdom and kindness,
the Dzo offered the creatures a gift.
From their branches
grew a magical glowing pod,
which had the incredible power
to transform one creature into another.
The pods gave them
the ability to understand each other,
which brought them all together.
But the wolf,
bitter that he had lost control
of the Valley,
despised this new way,
so he stole the Dzo's gift
to become a monster.
To become the Firewolf!
In order to destroy the pods,
he attacked the Dzo!
He slayed the first four!
Then drove the rest away.
Causing a rock slide,
which created a dam.
He banished the remaining Dzo
outside the Valley forever.
Without the Dzo,
he plunged the creatures of the Valley
back to a life of fear and mistrust.
And the Firewolf still rules the Valley
to this very day.
Hmm? Pretty good stuff, huh?
Eh.
"Eh"? What do you mean, "Eh"?
Where's the blood and guts? The gore?
What if the Firewolf
rips apart the Pinecone Hedgehogs
and feasts on their entrails?
That would be awesome.
You know what? That's your son.
We love you. We just want you to be safe.
- I know.
- Look around, kiddo.
This place, these Pookoo,
it's the one thing
you don't have to be afraid of.
That's why we're celebrating,
to give thanks for the piplet harvest.
We are very fortunate to have all of this.
Ready, set, pass the piplet!
A Javan?
I know we're not supposed to be curious.
Ollie!
I can smell you around here somewhere.
Hey, where are you?
Hey, Dad, don't worry. It's not dangerous.
It's smart. Look.
I taught it the trick.
I taught it how to eat.
Ollie.
What have you done?
Yup, that was it. Worst day of my life.
What's that saying?
Curiosity killed the cat.
I don't know what a cat is,
but my curiosity
definitely doomed the Pookoo.
The Javan, they're eating everything.
There's more every year.
- Take, take, take. That's all they do.
- But what about the emergency rations?
They're gone.
The storage is nearly empty.
How are we gonna make it
through the winter?
We need to find more piplets or… or…
Or what?
We starve.
Uh, Dad.
Hey, Dad. I was
up on the surface with my leaf camo.
And I… And I was able to find this.
Why did I have to feed that Javan?
Why? Huh? What is wrong with me?
It works?
Dad, it works!
Everybody, listen!
I found the solution!
Yes, yes, yes, yes!
Ah, okay.
Well, look who it is.
A hero.
Come on, let's go.
Big dumb sack of feathers.
Come and get me.
What are you waiting for? Come on!
Come on and get me!
Glowing pod?
From… the Tale?
It's true.
No. Nope, nope, nope, nope.
We're not doing this. Nope.
Don't need magic glowing pod thingies.
This is all your fault, you stupid Javan!
Ollie!
Come on.
Ollie! Hello?
Ollie!
My head.
Is that you?
Yeah. I'm down here!
He's here! Guys, I found him.
He's in the hole!
He is in a really, really dark hole.
- What are you doing there?
- Are you stuck, honey?
What's hurt?
Your ankle, leg, arm, ribs, back?
- Don't tell me it's your head!
- No, it's not.
I just feel a little weird.
Then come out already.
I'm coming.
Javan!
What? What? Where? Where?
Wait, wait. Whoa, I'm a…
No, no, no. I'm a--
Javan!
No, Mama! Help. Help me!
Ma, it's me!
Ollie?
Help me.
I'm scared, Ma.
Ollie's voice… coming from that bird?
Well, that means…
The bird ate Ollie!
The Javan ate Ollie!
No! Ollie!
- Calli!
- The Javan ate Ollie!
Whoa!
Pookoo Island?
Ah!
Whoa!
Javan! Javan! Javan!
Hello!
Ah! Ah! Ah!
Get back! Get… Get away from me!
Wait, wait, wait!
- Uh, Ivy?
- Stay back!
- Yes, Lily?
- Does he seem a little off?
A little? Look what you did to him, Ivy.
Get back, you!
Violet, stop being so dramatic.
He's fine.
Hey there, big guy. How you doing?
Stay back. Hey, you, stay back. Stay back.
That's an odd way to say thank you.
I saved your life.
Uh, we saved you.
If by "we," you mean me, all by myself,
without any help from you, as usual,
then, yes, we saved you.
Stay back! Don't you move.
You. And you, you!
I will use this!
Let's put the stick down.
Wow, you broke his brain.
I did not break his brain.
Hey there.
My name is Ivy. These are my sisters.
Um, we can actually introduce ourselves.
- I'm Violet.
- She's Violet.
- She's Lily.
- Hi!
You're just going to need
a teeny bit of medical attention,
so I'm gonna take you to Javan Rock.
Huh? Javan Rock?
Yes. Home, there.
I'm not going to Javan Rock.
That's not my home!
Okay, buddy. Easy.
Javan Rock has
everything we need to fix you up.
- Trust me on this.
- Trust you? Trust you?
That's hilarious.
Maybe the fall knocked his hearing around.
Do you understand me?
Oh, I understand. I understand just fine
what you and your cunning, thieving…
I… Wait, wait, wait. I…
I understand you.
How can I understand you?
Because I'm trapped.
It's because I'm trapped
inside the body of a Javan!
Get these feathers off me! Get 'em off!
Get these feathers off me!
Oh no, he's gone. What did we do?
- We? You mean what did she do?
- I'm stuck!
Not helping!
I'm stuck in here! Help! Somebody help me!
Help you? Help me!
I'm rolling dung here!
You gonna get out of my way?
You can talk too?
Yeah, that's right, genius,
and I'm talking to you.
Now get outta here. Move it.
Would you stop dawdling?
How long do I gotta wait for this dung?
Now you're gonna bust my chops too?
First, this idiot, and now you!
You don't have to yell.
How would I know?
They look like little dirt balls to me.
Um, Ivy, he's talking to bugs now.
About dung. Ivy, he's talking about dung.
Tell him what you did.
- Mmm, you mean heroically save his life?
- I think she means the, um, other thing?
Other things! Plural!
What are y'all talking about?
Okay, fine. When I was rescuing you,
I might have overestimated
your swimming ability.
- Wait. You dragged my head underwater?
- And?
And then I might have accidentally
brushed up against a pebble.
You did what?
There was also…
Okay, enough!
You were slippery. And quite heavy.
And I was a little shorthanded!
Wait, wait, wait. It's you!
You're that hero Javan
that knocked me into the pit.
Yes! I am a hero.
Thanks to me, you're safe now
from the angry little rat.
That angry little rat is me!
And I'm not a rat, I'm a Pookoo!
Pookoo? What's a Pookoo?
He's making up words now.
You still don't think you broke his brain?
- I did not break his brain!
- She broke your brain.
At most, you are mildly concussed,
which is why we have to take you home.
You're using that word again, "home."
What do you mean?
- Javan Rock.
- Javan Rock is not my home!
- What is that?
- No time for questions.
She doesn't like being questioned.
I don't mind!
There's just nothing to question,
so do what I say and fly!
I can't fly. Get off me!
- Ivy…
- Okay, plan B.
If it can't smell him, it can't eat him.
Lily, hold him down.
Violet, smear him with dung.
- What?!
- I am not touching that stuff.
Would it really kill you
to follow my lead just once?
Ugh, you're so bossy!
No, no! Not like that! Like this.
See how the feathers are caking up?
Just jam the dung
all the way down into the quill.
Aw, so cute. He's like a little dung baby.
Get to Javan Rock.
Lily, you're in charge while I'm gone.
- Yay!
- What?
- I'm older!
- It's not about who's oldest.
- Since when?
- Since I'm oldest.
Now do what I told Lily to tell you to do!
- Sodding tyrant.
- Good luck, dung baby!
Come on! Hurry!
Stay put. Trust me on this.
Huh, trust you?
Firewolf?
Dad was right?
Stupid pods and stupid birds.
Stupid transformations.
Ew.
Hi!
Ah!
- What you doing?
- Shh, there's a Firewolf around!
Firewolf? Where?
- What's a Firewolf?
- Shh! It's gone. I think.
Wait. I know you.
Didn't we meet a long time ago?
- Yes.
- I knew it!
One moment ago
counts as a long time, right?
- No.
- Oh, then no.
But I'm the only Boogle
in the lake, so yes!
Who are you?
Yeah, about that… Um…
It's hard to explain.
I'm in the wrong body.
Oh. Wrong body.
Sounds fun. How'd that happen?
I fell into this pit,
and there was this glowing pod
that my grandmother told me about,
from the Dzo.
These walking orchard things
from a long time ago.
Why am I bothering?
It doesn't make any sense.
Was it a pretty glowing pod?
Yeah.
Yep. I've seen those.
You have? You know where another one is?
Mmm, yeah, I do.
See that? It's right through the grove.
Look for the big round dead tree.
Got it. Glowing pod. Big round dead tree.
- Thanks! Wait, what's your name?
- Boogle. What's yours?
Ollie. Thanks, Boogle!
Big round dead tree, glowing pod.
- Big round dead tree, glowing pod.
- Um, hey there.
Buddy! Did we forget the whole part
when I clearly said "stay put"?
Turn me back to a Pookoo. Find the tree.
Glowing pod. Turn me back to a Pookoo.
- Smiling fish told me.
- Smiling fish. Magic glowing pods.
- A fish that was smiling told me. Whoa!
- It's getting worse.
Okay, stop!
You're gonna hurt yourself again.
What do you need?
I… I need that pod.
I… I need that pod to turn back, okay?
Into a Pookoo. A Pookoo.
When you get this magic pod,
promise you'll come to Javan Rock?
- Yeah, sure, whatever.
- Okay.
Here's your precious pod.
No, don't touch it!
- So you can turn back into a Pookoo…
- No, please! Stop!
…the strange creature you made up,
so we can get back to Javan Rock.
No!
No. Now, you promised.
Wait, what is that smell?
Why does everything smell so much?
No, no, no… Please, no.
Ah! Where are my beautiful feathers?
Where are my beautiful wings?
Oh, what are these
disgusting little claws?
- What did you do?!
- Wait, wait, wait, no. Excuse me.
What did I do?
You took my pod and became a Pookoo.
Pod? Pookoo?
Wait a second. I didn't break your brain?
- No!
- Oh, I knew it. Take that, Violet.
Why did you have to touch the pod? Why?!
Why didn't you tell me not to?
- I did!
- When?
Literally before you touched it.
Well, you obviously
didn't explain it very well
because if you had,
I would have understood it.
You know what? I'm done. I'm done!
I'm not wasting another second on you
because all you've done is ruin my life!
Oh, what is your problem?
You… You nut… You nut cake!
I don't know why you're so upset.
It is not like any of this is my fault.
Any? All. All your fault!
- Name one thing.
- You threw me into that pit.
Wait, you were the angry little rat
blinding the Javan.
I keep telling you I'm not a rat.
I'm a Pookoo!
Pookoo is a really stupid name,
by the way.
- You should've workshopped that more.
- It is not!
I mean, do you guys realize
it's got "poo" in the name?
I thought I hated you before, but now…
- You love me?
- No.
Oh, don't be ridiculous. I'm wonderful!
- Goodbye.
- Hey! Where do you think you're going?
- Nowhere.
- I don't believe you.
- I don't care.
- You're up to something.
You know how to find another pod.
- No.
- You're lying.
- I'm not.
- Fine. You won't mind if I follow you.
- Stop.
- Sorry, buster.
But from now on, I am your ride or die.
I choose die.
Wait. Boogle, Boogle! Great. Great.
Hey, Ollie, did you find the pod?
- No. It was stolen. Too much to explain.
- Excuse me! I did not steal it!
Ooh! Who's your friend, Ollie?
Nobody. She's nobody.
Quick. Tell me where to find another pod.
- You know, I do not appreciate--
- Hi, Nobody.
Boogle fish… talk?
- They do? Where?
- Stupid question. Yes, they can talk.
- You've been talking to him, right?
- Right.
But I just didn't
put it together until now.
- Because you're not very smart.
- Please. I'm brilliant.
Hello, Boogle!
- Why are you talking like that?
- I want him to understand.
He understands you just fine.
Unfortunately, we all understand you.
Can you tell me
where another pod is?
No. Don't trust her. She's a Javan.
They're all liars and thieves.
Well, all Pookoos are jealous,
petty little rodents.
Oh, when I get that pod, I can't wait
to drive all of you off my island.
Hey, hey. There's enough pods
for both of you.
I've seen 'em.
I've been alone my whole life.
Well, ever since
the great rock slide flooded the Valley.
So I've had a lot of time
to swim around and look at stuff.
Wow. The stuff I've seen.
Trees, shells, rocks,
scary rocks, not-so-scary rocks…
Yeah, okay, whatever. Scary rocks.
What about the pods?
From what I've seen,
the pretty glowy pods
are only on an old Dzo.
The Dzo.
- The great walking orchards?
- That's right.
The Javan used to live on their branches.
But… they disappeared.
Yeah, all but four dead ones.
Sorry. I know
it's a little scary to say "dead,"
but I don't know
how else to say not alive.
- Not living, dead ones.
- Okay, can we just stay on the pods?
Please. Where is
the next closest dead Dzo?
Oh yeah, that would be
by the Great Waterfall.
Yeah, it's a big one.
The Dzo, the waterfall. They're both big.
Where is this great waterfall?
It's across the Valley,
way beyond those cliffs.
Hey, there was something
I was gonna bring up,
but I don't know how you would feel if…
Ollie?
Nobody?
Anybody?
Here we go.
Why are you doing it that way?
Look at these paws. How is anyone
supposed to climb with these?
They're called wings. That's why we fly.
- I don't fly.
- You could if you tried.
Even baby Javans can fly.
What am I supposed to do?
Just raise my wings and--
Stupid wings.
You can't dig.
You can't grab things.
You can't climb. This is--
- They're completely useless.
- You cut that out.
You are a majestic creature.
Me, on the other hand,
I'm short, hairy, pretty much
everything in the Valley wants to eat me.
Don't flatter yourself.
I bet you taste terrible.
- Quick, get the dung!
- No time!
Smear me with the little dirt balls.
Turn me into a dung baby!
Dad? Dad? Where are you?
Wait, is that a baby Firewolf?
Where did you go?
Wolves talk?
Everything can talk
once you touch a pod. Keep up.
Poor thing's lost. Aw.
- He just needs some help.
- Aw, I know.
And then watch as it calls
its friends to ambush you
and ruins your life forever.
Okay, that's oddly specific.
- Hey, what's that smell?
- Would you just be quiet?
No. Oh, something really smells here.
Shh! That thing's dad
is out there somewhere.
He's right here.
There you are. What are you doing?
Looking for our prey.
You mean the ones getting away?
Fly! Embrace your Javan body!
- Flap, Ollie!
- Shut it! I'm trying to run here!
- Watch out!
- Whoa!
That was almost like flying.
- Run into the cave!
- What do you think I'm doing?
Why are…
Why aren't they following us in here?
Whoa!
Maybe it's because of that awful stench.
What does it smell like?
Hmm. I don't know. Ugh.
Describe it exactly.
Like a nightmare, but it's a smell.
I can taste it.
Where?
Everywhere.
We're in a Root Snake den.
No, no, no. Forget this. No. Not me.
Listen, I don't like you,
and you think you don't like me--
Keep it down. They're gonna hear us.
Ugh. Root Snakes are really
hard of hearing. They feel vibrations.
Okay.
Here's the plan.
We're gonna have to walk across the roots.
Um, speaking of hard of hearing.
I just said they feel vibrations,
and the roots and the snakes
look identical. So, no, no.
That's not gonna work.
I'm gonna come up with another plan.
Cut the bossy routine for one second
and listen to me.
You gotta use your Pookoo nose.
Pookoo can see smells.
Pookoo can see smells?
Okay, okay, first, close your eyes.
Close my eyes in a snake den?
Listen, no smell matters
except a stench right in front of you.
Oh, wow! You can see smells!
Ah, it's like having eyeballs
in your nose!
- Can we stay on task, please?
- Oh, right.
- Root.
- Our lives depend on it.
Are you absolutely sure?
Oh, yeah, I'm sure.
That's a root. Trust me on this.
Okay, okay, I've got this.
I can see that's a…
- Root Snake.
- Are you saying root or snake?
I am saying Root Snake.
See? The emphasis is on "snake."
When it's a "root,"
I put the emphasis on "root."
Just say "root" or "snake."
"Root" or "snake."
Okay, snake.
Good. Keep sniffing.
Okay, root. Go.
Root, root. Good, good.
Snake, definitely a snake.
Try that big one on the right.
Root.
Root. Step left.
No, snake!
This way. This way. Uh, stop.
Big step to your right.
There we go. Root.
Snake. Right.
Left. Snake, snake. That way.
Okay, root, root. Good.
Keep going ahead. Yep, yep, yep.
Almost there.
We're doing it. Well, mostly I'm doing it.
Hmm.
Supper.
Savory.
Starving.
That's not good.
Run.
Savory!
- Stuck.
- Sic 'em.
I think we can take 'em.
I'll go for the eyes, you wrestle 'em.
Are you nuts? No. You have to fly!
I told you! I don't fly!
We're gonna die!
Don't panic!
Focus on your lift, drag, and thrust!
Feel the rising air flowing
through your feathers!
What feathers? These?
No, those are your primaries!
I'm talking about your axials!
- Axi-what?
- Okay, Ollie. Flap or splat!
- Splat?!
- No, flap!
It's how every Javan learns to fly.
Trust me on this!
- I'm scared, Ivy!
- Then trust yourself!
Flap, Ollie, flap!
Ollie, you're flying.
Am I? I… I am?
- I am!
- Watch it!
Careful there!
That's it.
Yeah! You're a natural.
Whoo! This is great. This feels amazing!
Mmm, let's not attempt a flyby.
What was that? A flyby? Comin' right up!
Whoa! Careful.
Whoa, what's this?
It's an updraft. Just ride it.
Okay, Ollie. You can take us down now.
Did you just say "take us down"?
Ollie…
Ollie!
Whoo-hoo!
Whoo!
Why didn't you tell me
about flying sooner?
Um, I did. Several times.
Well, you obviously
didn't explain it very well
because if you had,
I would have understood it.
Thanks. You know, for…
- For pushing me back there.
- Oh!
You're welcome.
No one's ever thanked me
for being pushy before.
Okay. The Great Waterfall's
gotta be around here somewhere.
Let's try for it.
Mmm, we're losing light,
and it's too foggy.
We'll find it in the morning.
Ooh, I know that sound.
Somebody's hungry.
- I'm fine.
- Mm-hmm.
Sure.
Javan need to eat throughout the day.
So, by my estimate,
you're barely hanging on.
Here. Brush root. Helps fight the hunger.
Mmm.
Ugh!
You'll get used to it…
in a couple of years.
I can't… You…
You choose to eat this?
The Javan owe their lives to that stuff.
When the Dzo left,
we lost our food source.
The brush root kept the hunger down,
but only for so long.
The Javan almost starved.
I didn't know that.
We lost so many.
Friends, cousins,
aunts, uncles.
My mom and dad.
I was the oldest, so, um…
It was on me to find food for my sisters
so they didn't starve.
Not that they appreciate it
for a second, of course.
They just think of me
as a bossy, annoying big sis.
But if I don't look out for them,
who will?
That sounds like a… heavy burden.
Yeah.
Thank goodness I found the piplets.
They really saved us.
You what?
I discovered our new food source.
It was years ago.
Come to think of it,
that was the first time I met a Pookoo.
I didn't know what it was called,
but there was this little guy
who showed me
how to open the piplet seeds.
Huh.
You look exhausted.
I think it's time to hit the hay.
Good night, Ollie.
Oh, and Javan sleep upside down.
Just kidding!
Um, Ollie?
Ollie!
The Great Waterfall!
Look! There's the Dzo!
Dad, I'm hungry.
I know. You remind me every minute.
Because I'm hungry!
Wolves! It's a wolf den.
Hey, guys!
Oh, thank goodness. I didn't get
a chance to tell you before, but--
Yeah, the wolf den.
Yeah, pretty important, the wolf den.
There's no way in.
I have a way to get you in.
Don't worry. I'm gonna distract them.
Wait, wait. You'd do that for us?
Well… you guys are my only friends.
And when you change back,
I won't have any friends anymore, so…
So I was hoping maybe you could…
Get you a pod!
You could become a Javan.
Or a Pookoo.
They've got a killer schnoz.
Oh… A Pookoo…
Aw, ah! That would be great!
We are getting you a pod, Boogle.
That's a promise.
Thank you. Okay, now hurry.
You won't have much time.
But wait. How are you gonna distract
the wolves?
I'm gonna be their lunch.
That is one big fish.
I call dibs on the head.
Dad, you're letting it get away!
The pods! The pods!
But there's only one.
No, there's gotta be more.
The Boogle said there are plenty of 'em.
We don't have much time.
I'll just take it.
Hey. Wait, wait, wait. Why?
I'll be a Javan again.
We can fly around together
and find another one.
What? You don't trust me?
You don't trust me?
Ouch.
Okay. Well, my community is relying on me.
Oh, and mine isn't?
Come on. It's not the same,
not even by a long shot.
I'll have you know,
it's my job to make sure
the Javan fatten up for the winter.
Fatten up?
Yes, and our piplets are running low.
Your piplets?
- Yes.
- You mean the ones you took from me?
What? I have never taken anything
from you.
You really don't remember, do you?
Remember what?
Ollie, what are you talking about?
The little Pookoo
who taught you how to open the piplets?
That was me.
You ate everything,
you ran us underground,
and now we live off your scraps.
My dad told me outsiders
weren't to be trusted,
but I didn't listen. I never listen!
And it's all my fault
because I was so gullible
and naive and stupid!
We're not gonna survive the winter.
Do you understand that?
We're gonna starve.
I…
It's all my fault.
You know…
My own father…
He won't even look me in the eye.
And it's all because
I trusted you.
Boogle!
- Help, Boogle!
- Boogle! Help!
Boogle! Boogle!
Help!
Ollie?!
And Nobody?
You're Boogles? What happened?
Uh, there was only one pod,
and we said "Boogle"
just before we touched it.
Now that I think about it, I said "Pookoo"
before I touched the other pod.
That must be how the pods work.
You become whatever you say.
Great. That'll help us
when we go back in time
and do this over again.
Ivy, we're fish.
Thanks to you, I'm even further away
from getting home and saving my village.
- Ollie, listen--
- Look.
You're a Javan.
I'm a Pookoo.
We were always meant to be separate.
This is where we say goodbye.
So…
Bye, Ollie! I'll miss you!
Have a great life as a Boogle!
I'll just tell Ivy
about the other pods, then.
There's a whole bunch of 'em!
So long, Ollie!
I'll always remember you!
Hey, I don't mean to pry,
but you two don't seem
to be getting along too well.
Yeah. It is what it is.
These pods, see,
they're at the top of Scary Rock Falls.
I'm afraid to even say the words.
Scariest place in the Valley.
We need to work together
to make it up there,
so you two need to make up quick, okay?
Okay. I'll let you two in on
a little secret.
You see me, and you probably think,
"Wow, Boogle has it all."
Brains, looks, charm, brains.
But the truth is,
Boogle doesn't have it all.
I spent my whole life wandering this lake,
knowing something was missing.
Then I realized what it was.
I was all alone.
And I can tell you,
when you're alone for so long…
you go into some dark, dark places.
What I mean is,
it makes you really appreciate
why we need each other.
Ollie.
I am…
When we were kids,
you were the first Pookoo I'd ever met.
My sisters hadn't eaten in days.
And I was scared.
But something about you made me trust you.
You were kind to me.
You showed me how to eat the piplets.
And then you were gone.
I never knew where you went.
But… I never forgot you.
And, Ollie…
I never knew how much I hurt you.
I am so, so sorry.
Look!
We are here!
Scary Rock Falls.
Pods! Tons of pods!
I'm going for it! I'm going for it!
Yeah, tried that.
The waterfall's too strong
for a single Boogle,
but not for thriple Boogle.
Form Megafish!
- Megafish?
- Megafish. Right.
Lock fins and swim together. Megafish!
Swim as one!
- Whoo!
- All right. One down. Two to go.
Yeah, baby!
What am I seeing? What is this?
Fish?
- Fish?
- Fish.
Fish?
What are those?
Those? Those are the scary rocks.
Fish!
Reform Megafish!
Almost there!
Okay, now what do we do?
Come on, now, anybody.
Ah, Dad!
Now's our chance.
What are we waiting for? Let's go!
The pup! Grab my tail!
- Whoo!
- Yes!
We made it.
How did you even do all of that?
Me? You had moves back there.
You're a natural.
You hear that?
The Dzo.
That's them.
How about this? Together, on three.
- One, two, three!
- Pookoo!
- Javan!
- Yeah! Thank you!
- Yes! I'm back!
I'm back, baby!
Hey, guys!
Hey, Boogle. What are you gonna become?
I was just trying to decide that.
A Pookoo, a Javan,
a Pinecone Hedgehog, or…
Or, wait. I know.
Maybe I could just become the…
Firewolf!
Boogle?
There was never Boogle.
There was only ever
me.
The Tale.
You're the one… You tore the Valley apart.
You created the dam.
You drove the Dzo out.
Yes, yes, and yes.
I'm good. What can I say?
But why? You ruined everything.
There was so much peace here,
and you destroyed it.
- You caused so much pain.
- What about my pain?!
I was the runt of my litter,
so my pack tossed me aside to die,
and none of the other creatures
wanted me around.
So I promised myself that one day
I would burn the Valley down
and those who survived
would bow down to me.
I ruled this place
until those tree monsters
sent one last pod
and trapped me in that hideous fish body.
The pods.
I waited ages for someone to come along.
Some gullible, trusting fool like you!
"Oh, Ollie. You'd do that for me? Wow."
"You're my best friend."
Did you even think about any of this?
You thought that pack of puny Tree Wolves
were Firewolves?
Ivy!
No, no, no, no, no! Ivy! Ivy!
"Ivy! Ivy!"
What are you crying about?
You wanted to get rid of her, didn't you?
You think she's your friend?
There are no friends in the Valley.
It's time the Valley
was ruled by fear again.
Ollie.
He's wrong about you.
Keep
your heart
open.
No, no, no, no, no, no! Ivy! Ivy!
No.
I'm gonna get you to Javan Rock.
Ivy?
Help her.
Ivy! Ivy!
Where's Ivy?
Oh, I'm sorry, love.
She's… gone.
Ivy…
No.
I'm so sorry.
You were…
the best friend…
I ever had.
There, there.
Don't stop saying
all those nice things about me.
How could you be here if she…
But she said you were gone.
Gone to get you some food.
I was right, you know.
You still are that kind little Pookoo.
Yeah, well, that kind little Pookoo…
always seems to mess everything up.
Let me show you something.
Boo!
Hey, you boys hear
about my brother's nest? Water damage.
- Me grandson could help.
- Yeah?
Oh, yeah. He's good at fixing stuff.
Good at breaking it too!
Flap or splat!
Flap or splat! Flap or splat!
Ooh!
He splatted!
I'm okay.
I know this won't change the hurt
we, and I, caused your community.
And for that, I am truly sorry.
I want you to know,
not everything you do turns out bad.
All of their parents
were saved by the piplets
that you showed me how to eat.
None of them would be here without you.
Thank you.
That's him! That's Ollie!
- He's so cute!
- Such a big nose!
Why's he so fluffy?
How did he fly up here
with such small wings?
Ah, I can't fly, as a Pookoo.
He can talk!
Hi, Dung Baby! Remember us?
- We covered you in dung.
- Yeah, I remember.
But thank you. You saved me.
Look! It's snowing!
- It's snowing!
- I love snow!
It's snowing! Wow!
- It's snowing!
- Yes! No school!
It's snowing!
This isn't snow.
Firewolf.
The fire is spreading fast.
The skies aren't safe.
Get everyone to their nests!
We need to help the Valley.
Wait! Everyone stop!
We have to help.
It's too dangerous.
We have to look after our own.
Everyone, listen up!
Now, my big sister may be bossy
and annoying and overbearing…
Some might actually even say tyrannical--
Hold on!
I'm talking.
Not only does she interrupt,
she talks too much.
Also, her plume is annoyingly big.
These are all things
we obviously agree on. But…
She has always risked herself
to take care of us.
And we wouldn't be here without her.
She thinks I don't know that, but I do.
Look, she may not always be right,
but she is definitely right about this.
The Valley needs our help.
Violet's right about Ivy being right.
All these creatures! They're trapped!
Let's help them out.
We can lead them to the shore.
That is a great idea, Violet.
We'll do the same.
Stay close!
It's okay. We're here to help.
Uh…
Pookoo Island.
It's the only safe place left.
How are we gonna get them there?
Thank you for saving my son.
What do you say?
Thank you!
We can help.
All aboard!
No time for lollygagging! No panic!
My hero!
Let's move out!
- Ollie?
- He's alive?
Mom! Dad! I need your help!
Ollie!
No!
Ivy!
Watch out! Get away from those things!
Dad, listen to me. It's not an attack.
These are the creatures of the Valley.
They don't have anywhere else to go.
They need help.
Dad.
They need our help.
Help me bring them onto the island.
We can't do that, Ollie.
Never trust anything but a Pookoo.
You know this.
No, Dad, the Tale. It's all true.
The Dzo, the Firewolf, the pods.
I've used those pods
to become the creatures of the Valley,
and I've learned something.
We're stronger
together.
Dad, I know you're scared.
But we have to trust each other.
Ollie!
We don't have much time.
Follow me.
- What's the plan?
- The Firewolf said it himself.
The Dzo set the pod to trap him once.
Maybe we can do it again.
Are you sure about this?
Nope.
Dzo, are you out there?
Can you hear me?
Ollie, hurry!
All I need is one more pod.
Can you send me one more pod?
Please, please, please.
The Valley needs your help.
Please.
Dzo.
The Dzo.
It can't be.
Okay, Ollie, we've got this.
Ollie?
That's our son.
Stay away from them.
Ollie, you found another pod.
Oh, you noticed.
Gullible little Firewolf.
I liked you better as a…
Boogle!
You thought I wouldn't be ready
for the same pathetic trap.
Who's the gullible one now?
Ollie, Ollie, Ollie…
What are you gonna do now?
You can't jump in the water
because it's too deep,
and Dzos sink.
Watch your step, Ollie!
You think you're a Dzo?
Restoring peace and harmony to the Valley.
You're just an angry little rat
fighting in vain for what's yours.
Only this time, it's your life.
This is my valley now.
What?
No.
It's our valley.
No, no, no. No.
What are you doing? Stop.
You have to stop.
Hey. Trust me on this.
No!
Ollie!
Ollie! Ollie!
You're alive!
Ah! I thought you were gone forever!
Where… How did you… I…
The Dzo. They found me.
You know, they have
these things called, uh, magic pods.